Walt Whitman Collection
Walt Whitman Collection
1860-1957
1860-1892
0.5 linear ft.
American poet. Collection contains correspondence (incoming and outgoing), printed material, clippings, one reel film.
3181659
Biographical History
Walt Whitman (1819-1892) was an influential and well-known American poet, essayist and journalist. Among his best-known works are poems "I Sing the Body Electric" and "Song of Myself," and the poetry collection Leaves of Grass. He is buried at Harleigh Cemetery in Camden, New Jersey, where he lived for the last twenty years of his life.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Walt Whitman Collection consists of clippings, correspondence, one media item, and printed material.
Clippings consists of a scrapbook of clippings about Whitman and his work, compiled by William Douglas O'Connor and included his annotations on the articles.
The bulk of Correspondence is incoming, mostly from friends such as clergyman William Sloane Kennedy, publisher James Gordon Bennett, author William Douglas O'Connor, and journalist and reformer James Redpath. A complete list of correspondents is given in the inventory below.
Media consists of one reel of 16mm film, an 11-minute sequence consisting of a short biography of Whitman and one of his poems set to a scenic background. The film canister is labeled "color" but the accompanying card says "black and white."
Printed material contains a prospectus for book, a reprint of "At the Graveside of Walt Whitman," and several items related to a 1957 exhibit on Whitman mounted by the Rumanian Institute for Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical.
Related Material
Whitman-related material may be found in several other collections, particulatly the Charles Wharton Stork Papers and the Frederick P. Hier Papers. Please search the manuscript collections for "Whitman" to locate all relevant material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Whitman, Walt.; Poets, American.; 16mm (photographic film size); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Prospectuses.; Scrapbooks.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Access to media requires advance notice to produce a use copy.
Acquisition Information
Unspecified, 1964.
Inventory
- Clippings
  - Scrapbook of critics' newspaper columns, 1860-1887; compiled by William Douglas O'Connor, with his handwritten notes (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1860-1889 (Box 1)
    Correspondents:
    W. Angus, Mary Ashley
    Herbert J. Bathgate, James Gordon Bennett, R. Brisbane, John Burroughs
    Edward Carpenter, Matt H. Carpenter
    J. Chamberlin, Henry Clapp, Richard W. Colles, M. Daniel Conway
    William Sloane Kennedy
    F.C. MacDonald, Joseph B. Marvin
    William Douglas O'Connor, Nelly O'Connor
    Edward Potter
    James Redpath, Ernest Rhys, A. Rice, Thomas William Rolleston
    Rudolf Schmidt, Susan Garnet Smith, Louisa Sowdon
    Ticknor and Fields
    Allen Upward
  - Outgoing, 1887-1889; 1892 (Box 1)
  - Of others, related to Whitman, 1891-1892; letters and telegrams from J.W. Wallace to H. Buxton Forman, concerning Whitman's ill-health (Box 1)
- Media
  - A Carol of Harvest, 3/21/1957; whitman_w_001; visual interpretation of Walt Whitman's famous poem; includes old label and handwritten note, which reads: "Bio and poem of W. Whitman against a scenic background".; Film: 16mm; running time 11:00
- Printed material
  - Miscellaneous, 1892; 1893,; 1957; prospectus for book; reprint of article "At the Graveside of Walt Whitman"; items related to exhibit by Rumania Institute for Cultural Relations with Foreign Countries (Box 1)